Finding aid to the Laura Woolsey Lord Scales Papers CA.MS.00088
Smith College Archives
Laura Woolsey Lord Scales Papers
1870-1990
Smith College Archives
Scales, Laura Woolsey Lord.
CA.MS.00088
2.083 linear feet (5 containers)
Graduate, class of 1901, Smith College; Dean of Students, Smith College; and Dean of Women, Carnegie Institute of Technology. Papers include clippings, diaries, commonplace books, geneology, photographs, passports, speeches, recipes and writings, including her autobiography, poetry, and articles. Correspondents include her family and friends, plus the Morrow Family and William Allan Neilson.
Biographical / Historical
Laura Woolsey Lord was born on November 13, 1879 in Hanover, New Hampshire, where she spent all of her childhood and most of her adolescence. She completed high school at Miss Frances Emerson's boarding school in Boston before entering Smith College as an undergraduate. Scales, a member of the class of 1901, attended Smith while it was still relatively new and the reputation of the College depended on the students' public decorum. By this time, women were accepted as students even if they were not yet encouraged to pursue higher education and Scales did not consider herself a pioneer in women's education.
After college Scales married Robert Latham Scales, who had been courting her while she was at Smith. The two were married just four years when he died of tuberculosis. After his death, Scales, now twenty-eight years old, was forced to enter the workforce. Although it was not easy during these times for women to find public employment, Scales was soon offered a position as an instructor at the Boston Museum of Fine Arts. She spent seven years there before accepting the duty as dean of women at the Carnegie Institute of Technology in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. She was only employed there for two years before she was offered a similar position in 1922 and returned to her alma mater, Smith College.
As Smith College "warden," Scales served as the dean of students, in charge of housing students, chaperoning on-campus activities, and arranging guest visits to the College. In addition, Scales chaired the committee of social activities and was a member of the conference committee. Scales was extremely dedicated to improving the campus atmosphere for students. As an undergraduate, Scales had lived off-campus and as a result, felt that she had not experienced much of the campus life, activity, and camaraderie that went on in the dormitories. One of the first changes she instilled as warden was to require that all students live on-campus. This decision added to the family atmosphere that Smith had always prided itself on and thus helped to unify the students and increase school spirit. Scales also valued the opinions of the students and met regularly with members of the Student Government Association in order to ensure that Smith kept up with the ever-changing educational customs and social trends. In addition, it was also Scales' responsibility to make sure that the rules and regulations of Smith College paralleled those in students' homes. Scales served as warden for twenty-two years before retiring in 1944.
During her time at Smith, Scales remained an active member of her community and her influence reached far beyond the Smith gates. She spent twenty-six years on the board of trustees at the People's Institute, a Northampton community center, and also served on the advisory committee of the Girls City Club of Northampton. In 1931, Scales was awarded an honorary degree from Smith and in 1939 she became the third woman ever to receive an honorary doctor of literature degree from Dartmouth College. In 1936, Smith College showed their appreciation for all that she had done for the school by naming one of the new dormitories the Laura Scales House.
After her retirement, Scales spent thirty years in Dunedin, Florida before returning to Northampton, Massachusetts. To Scales, education was "the backbone of living. It makes the world interesting." This mentality stayed with her for her whole life; she lived to be one hundred ten years old and remained an avid reader almost until her dying day. She died on June 12, 1990 in her Northampton nursing home.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into three series:
I. Biography
II. Correspondence
III. Writings and Speeches
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Laura Woolsey Lord Scales Papers were donated to the College Archives by Laura Lord Smail, Class of 1944.
Scope and Contents
Papers include clippings, diaries, commonplace books, geneology, photographs, passports, speeches, recipes and writings, including her autobiography, poetry, and articles. Correspondents include her family and friends, plus the Morrow Family and William Allan Neilson.
Scales, Laura Woolsey Lord.; Smith College--Faculty.; Smith College--Students.; Smail, Laura Lord; Smail, Laura Lord
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHY
  - Clippings, 1936-1990; undated (Box 1007)
  - Commonplace Book, 1894-1903 (Box 1007)
  - Diaries, 1904-1907; 1935 (Box 1007)
  - Financial Records, 1909-1912; 1923-1980 (Box 1007)
  - Genealogy, 1931; undated (Box 1007)
  - Honorary degree (Smith), 1931 (Box 1007)
  - Honorary degree (Dartmouth), 1939 (Box 1007)
  - List of possessions, 1968-1980 (Box 1007)
  - Miscellaneous, 1920-1985; undated (Box 1007)
  - Obituaries, 1990 (Box 1007)
  - Passports, 1922-1932 (Box 1007)
  - Photographs, 1870s-1990 (Box 1008)
  - Photograph album, 1909-1912 (Box 1008)
  - Recipe Notebook, undated (Box 1008)
  - Robert Leighton Scales, 1908; undated (Box 1008)
  - Smith College appointment, 1922 (Box 1008)
  - Smith College retirement, 1944 (Box 1008)
  - Tributes, 1920; 1951; undated (Box 1008)
  - Tributes 100th birthday, 1979 (Box 1008)
  - Wedding, 1904-1908 (Box 1008)
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE
  - A - D, 1908-1965; undated (Box 1009)
  - E - K, 1908-1977; undated (Box 1009)
  - L - R, 1917-1986; undated (Box 1009)
  - S - Z, 1912-1987; undated (Box 1009)
  - Huger Elliot, 1923-1940 (Box 1009)
  - Alice S. Emerson, 1902-1924; undated (Box 1009)
  - Henry Gow, 1913-1934 (Box 1009)
  - Elizabeth Deerling Hanscom, 1908-1959 (Box 1009)
  - Morrow Family, 1933-1978; undated (Box 1009)
  - William Allan Neilson, 1933-1946 (Box 1009)
  - Patricia Nichols Page, 1968-1973 (Box 1009)
  - Jean Mitchell Pennington, 1941-1959 (Box 1009)
  - Robert Leighton Scales, 1907-1908 (Box 1009)
  - Mira Bigelow Wilson, 1952-1953 (Box 1009)
  - Lester Wing, 1917-1923 (Box 1009)
  - re death of mother, 1931 (Box 1009)
  - unidentified and fragments, 1908-1915; undated (Box 1009)
- SERIES III. WRITINGS AND SPEECHES
  - Autobiography correspondence and records, 1976-1977 (Box 1010)
  - Autobiography m.s., 1975 (Box 1010)
  - Poetry, 1912; undated (Box 1010)
  - "The Museum as an Introduction to History", 1916 (Box 1010)
  - "The Museum's Part in the Making of Americans", 1917 (Box 1010)
  - "The Holidays of Art", 1918 (Box 1010)
  - War Industries, Yesterday and Today, 1918 (Box 1010)
  - "The Schools and the Museum of Fine Arts", 1919 (Box 1010)
  - "Art and the Present Hour", 1920 (Box 1010)
  - "Boys of the Ages" correspondence, 1922 (Box 1010)
  - "Boys of the Ages": ms., 1922 (Box 1010)
  - "Boys of the Ages" (two published copies), 1922 (Box 1010)
  - "Shall We Fear the Large College?", 1922 (Box 1010)
  - "Locking the Barn Door", 1924 (Box 1010)
  - "A College Warden Speaks", 1931 (Box 1010)
  - "Smith College Cooperative Houses", 1934 (Box 1010)
  - SAQ article re trip, 1935 (Box 1010)
  - Chapel talks, 1938 (Box 1010)
  - Speeches, Misc., 1928-1971 (Box 1010)
  - "Adjusting Yourself to the Modern World, undated (Box 1011)
  - "Art as an Americanizing Force", undated (Box 1011)
  - "Changing Tendencies in Bringing up Children", undated (Box 1011)
  - "Even Unto these Last", undated (Box 1011)
  - "Ex Patria", undated (Box 1011)
  - "In Transit", undated (Box 1011)
  - "Life's Day", undated (Box 1011)
  - "Madonna and the Boy", undated (Box 1011)
  - "Matsuyama Mirror", undated (Box 1011)
  - "The Measure of Heaven", undated (Box 1011)
  - "Not Only Wise", undated (Box 1011)
  - "Old Age", undated (Box 1011)
  - "Old Tales from China and Japan", undated (Box 1011)
  - "On Principle", undated (Box 1011)
  - "The Singing of the Pine Tree: A New World Legend, undated (Box 1011)
  - "Stories for Children", undated (Box 1011)
  - "Where Your Treasure Is", undated (Box 1011)
  - "Women's Colleges and Women's Conduct", undated (Box 1011)
  - Speeches and Writings: Fragments, undated (Box 1011)